Are you all right, Your Royal Highness?
‫هل أنت بخير يا صاحب السموّ؟
What happened, Your Royal Highness?
‫ماذا حدث يا صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
Well, you see,
‫حسنًا، كما ترى،
there was a minor accident.
‫وقع حادث بسيط.
Goodness. What happened here?
‫يا للهول، ماذا حدث هنا؟
I'll get someone to clean this up right away.
‫سأحضر شخصًا لتنظيف هذا حالًا.
But what are you doing here, Royal Tutor Jung?
‫لكن ماذا تفعل هنا ‫أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ"؟
Royal Scholar Yang wanted me to escort His Royal Highness.
‫طلب مني ‫العالم الملكي "يانغ" أن أرافق سموّه.
I just told him that His Royal Highness wouldn't be able to attend the lecture.
‫أخبرته للتو ‫أن صاحب السموّ لن يتمكن من حضور المحاضرة.
I should just attend the lecture today.
‫يجب أن أحضر المحاضرة اليوم.
Go tell him I changed my mind.
‫اذهب وأخبره أنني غيّرت رأيي.
But Your Royal Highness…
‫لكن يا صاحب السموّ الملكي…
ZUO ZHUAN
‫"تسوه جوهان"
Your Royal Highness. Goodness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي، يا للهول.
EPISODE 6
‫"الحلقة السادسة"
"Chunjisaenggi gwancheolsasi
‫"تشونجيساينغي غوانتشيولساسي
chunjeukchunjisaeng
‫تشونجيوكتشونجيساينغ
hajeukchunjijang
‫هاجيوكتشونجيجانغ
chujeukchunjisu
‫تشوجيوكتشونجيسو
dongjeukchunjijang."
‫دونغجيوكتشونجيجانغ."
"Spring is born in spring.
‫"يُولد الربيع في الربيع.
Spring grows in summer.
‫ينمو الربيع في الصيف.
Spring is harvested in autumn.
‫يُحصد الربيع في الخريف.
And spring is treasured in winter."
‫ويُدّخر الربيع في الشتاء."
That is correct.
‫هذا صحيح.
Gosh, Royal Tutor Jung. His Royal Highness is already here.
‫عجبًا، أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ"، ‫وصل صاحب السموّ.
I thought you went to get him. Where have you been?
‫ظننت أنك ذهبت لإحضاره، أين كنت؟
Well, there was an accident.
‫حسنًا، وقع حادث.
An accident? What happened to your finger?
‫حادث؟ ماذا أصاب إصبعك؟
Why…
‫لماذا…
You must be having an awful hangover too.
‫لا بد أنك تعاني من آثار ثمالة فظيعة أيضًا.
"So the scholar said
‫"لذا قال العالم
the best of the four morals is similar to the best virtue of the five, sympathy.
‫إن أفضل ما في الأخلاق الأربعة يشبه ‫أفضل فضيلة من الخمس، التعاطف.
If we decide to look at the moral values individually, there are many values.
‫إن قررنا أن ننظر إلى القيم الأخلاقية ‫بشكل فردي، فهناك الكثير من القيم.
But if we look at them as a whole, one value includes all four moral values.
‫لكن إن نظرنا إليها ككل، فإن قيمة واحدة ‫تشمل جميع القيم الأخلاقية الأربع.
And this is the truth."
‫وهي الحقيقة."
"All these moral values make up the truth.
‫"كل هذه القيم الأخلاقية تشكل الحقيقة.
And the universal truth
‫والحقيقة الكونية
will be clear as day."
‫ستكون واضحة وضوح الشمس."
Do you understand?
‫هل تفهم؟
Why are you staring at each other?
‫لماذا تحدّقان ببعضكما؟
I… I wasn't staring at him.
‫لم أكن أحدّق به.
And your face
‫ووجهك…
is the same color as wine.
‫له نفس لون النبيذ.
What is it, Your Royal Highness?
‫ما الأمر يا صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
I forgot to bring my book.
‫نسيت أن أُحضر كتابي.
You have your book here.
‫كتابك هنا.
The book for the evening lecture.
‫كتاب المحاضرة المسائية.
I see.
‫فهمت.
Excuse me.
‫المعذرة.
You shouldn't trouble yourself for it.
‫يجب ألّا تزعج نفسك بذلك.
Please stay here. I'll take care of it.
‫ابق هنا من فضلك، سأهتم بالأمر.
Royal Tutor Jung.
‫أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ".
Yes?
‫نعم؟
You must have a lot of time on your hands today.
‫لا بد أن لديك الكثير من وقت الفراغ اليوم.
No. I have a lot of work to do.
‫لا، لديّ الكثير من العمل لأنجزه.
Okay. Whatever. Go and bring a book from the Crown Prince's office.
‫حسنًا، لا يهم، ‫اذهب وأحضر كتابًا من مكتب وليّ العهد.
His Royal Highness needs it for the evening lecture.
‫صاحب السموّ الملكي يريده ‫من أجل المحاضرة المسائية.
Go now. Come on, hurry up.
‫اذهب الآن، هيا، بسرعة.
"Chunjeukmanmulsisaeng
‫"تشونجيوكمانمولسيساينغ.
Hajeuk…"
‫هاجيوك…"
DAXUE YANYI
‫"داشوي يانيي"
ZUO ZHUAN
‫"تسوه جوهان"
"Manmuljangyang…"
‫"مانمولجانغيانغ…"
No.
‫لا.
What is it?
‫ما الأمر؟
Your Royal Highness!
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي!
Where are you going? Your Royal Highness!
‫إلى أين تذهب؟ يا صاحب السموّ الملكي!
Did I do something to upset him?
‫هل فعلت شيئًا أغضبه؟
ZUO ZHUAN
‫"تسوه جوهان"
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
Why do you have this book?
‫لماذا تملك هذا الكتاب؟
ZUO ZHUAN
‫"تسوه جوهان"
What are you doing with that book?
‫ماذا تفعل بذلك الكتاب؟
That is not the one you were supposed to get.
‫ليس هذا ما كان يجب أن تحضره.
I have it because that book belongs to me.
‫الكتاب بحوزتي لأنه يخصّني.
But this book
‫لكن هذا الكتاب
is Dam-i's. No.
‫ملك لـ"دامي"، لا.
I transcribed it myself for a girl I liked.
‫نسخته بنفسي من أجل فتاة كنت أحبها.
I have no idea what you're talking about.
‫لا أعلم ما الذي تتحدث عنه.
I'll look for the book myself.
‫سأبحث عن الكتاب بنفسي.
I want you to leave now.
‫أريدك أن تغادر الآن.
You really don't remember a court maid named Dam-i?
‫ألا تتذكر حقًا خادمة بلاط تُدعى "دامي"؟
When you were the Prince,
‫عندما كنت أميرًا،
I had a private audience with you.
‫حظيت بلقاء خاص معك.
And you personally gave me the present she left for me.
‫وأنت شخصيًا أعطيتني الهدية التي تركتها لي.
The palace is full of court maids.
‫القصر مليء بخادمات البلاط.
How can I remember something that happened so long ago?
‫كيف يمكنني ‫أن أتذكّر شيئًا حدث منذ وقت طويل جدًا؟
But…
‫لكنك…
you remembered me.
‫تذكرتني.
When we first met at the courtesan house,
‫عندما التقينا أول مرة في بيت الدعارة،
you remembered who I was.
‫تذكرت من أكون.
That's…
‫هذا…
I only remembered you
‫تذكرتك أنت فقط
because I thought you were good at flattery even for a brazen boy.
‫لأنني ظننت ‫أنك تجيد التملق حتى بالنسبة لشاب وقح.
Does that answer your question?
‫هل يجيب هذا على سؤالك؟
ZUO ZHUAN
‫"تسوه جوهان"
Dam-i?
‫"دامي"؟
The court maid I liked when I was young.
‫خادمة البلاط التي أحببتها في صغري.
I see.
‫فهمت.
The girl you fell in love with at first sight from the banquet?
‫الفتاة التي وقعت في غرامها ‫من النظرة الأولى أثناء إقامة المأدبة؟
The Crown Prince had the book I gave to the girl.
‫كان الكتاب الذي أعطيته ‫للفتاة بحوزة وليّ العهد.
The Crown Prince?
‫وليّ العهد؟
Why do you think
‫برأيك،
Dam-i just disappeared like that? She didn't even say goodbye to me.
‫لماذا اختفت "دامي" فجأة؟ لم تودّعني حتى.
If she's still alive,
‫إن كانت ما تزال حية
she's probably already married, right?
‫فربما تكون قد تزوجت، صحيح؟
And she must have kids who look just like her too, right?
‫ولا بد أن لديها أطفالًا ‫يشبهونها تمامًا أيضًا، صحيح؟
What a surprise.
‫يا لها من مفاجأة.
I didn't know you could be a hopeless romantic too.
‫لم أعلم ‫أنك قد تكون رومانسيًا يائسًا أيضًا.
Didn't you tell me that you went to Ming
‫ألم تخبرني أنك ذهبت إلى "مينغ"
because women in Joseon weren't good enough for you?
‫لأن النساء في "جوسون" ‫لم يكنّ مناسبات بما يكفي بالنسبة لك؟
What about you? Is there someone you like?
‫ماذا عنك؟ هل أنت مُعجب بفتاة ما؟
Someone I like?
‫فتاة تعجبني؟
You're handsome and rich.
‫أنت وسيم وثري.
On top of that, you're a member of the royal family with a heart of gold.
‫علاوة على ذلك، ‫أنت فرد من العائلة الملكية وتتحلى باللطف.
There is someone.
‫هناك فتاة.
There is? Who is it?
‫حقًا؟ من هي؟
Whose clan is she from? Or is she a distant relative?
‫من أي عشيرة هي؟ ‫أم تربطك بها صلة قرابة بعيدة؟
Is she pretty? Is she kind?
‫هل هي جميلة؟ هل هي لطيفة؟
Don't tell me
‫لا تقل لي
you already set the date.
‫إنك سبق وحددت الموعد.
She's very beautiful
‫إنها جميلة جدًا
and warmhearted too.
‫وطيبة القلب أيضًا.
How come you didn't say anything to me?
‫لماذا لم تخبرني بأي شيء؟
So when will you introduce me to her?
‫إذًا متى ستعرّفني عليها؟
I'm a good judge of character when it comes to ladies.
‫أُجيد الحكم على الشخصيات ‫عندما يتعلق الأمر بالسيدات.
I'm not sure.
‫لست متأكدًا.
I don't even know if I'll be able to do so.
‫لا أعرف حتى إذا كنت سأتمكن من فعل ذلك.
Don't tell me
‫لا تقل لي
this is a one-sided love.
‫إنه حب من طرف واحد.
You had a busy couple of days.
‫كانت الأيام القليلة الماضية حافلة.
You seem quite fatigued.
‫تبدو متعبًا جدًا.
Why don't you go to sleep early, Your Royal Highness?
‫لم لا تخلد ‫إلى النوم باكرًا يا صاحب السموّ؟
Wait.
‫مهلًا.
Yes, Your Royal Highness?
‫نعم يا صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
Do you know how my record…
‫هل تعرفين كيف سُوّي سجلّي…
No.
‫لا.
Do you know how Dam-i's record
‫هل تعرفين شيئًا عن سجلّ "دامي"
has been settled?
‫وكيف تمت تسويته؟
Why are you asking me that?
‫ما مناسبة هذا السؤال؟
It is in my knowledge
‫على حد علمي
that your mother had taken care of it when she was alive.
‫فإن أمك اهتمت بالأمر ‫حين كانت على قيد الحياة.
DAM-I
‫"دامي"
DAY 21 OF MONTH 4
‫"(دامي)، يوم 21 من الشهر الرابع"
LEFT THE PALACE DUE TO ILLNESS
‫"غادرت القصر بسبب المرض"
What is this regarding?
‫بم يتعلق هذا الأمر؟
Why did you come all the way here this morning
‫لماذا قطعتما ‫كل هذه المسافة إلى هنا هذا الصباح
to meet an imprisoned physician?
‫لمقابلة طبيب مسجون؟
I'm embarrassed to ask you for a favor,
‫أخجل أن أطلب منك خدمة،
but my daughter made a promise to the physician.
‫لكن ابنتي قطعت وعدًا للطبيب.
So I came here to ask for your help despite my sense of shame.
‫لذلك أتيت إلى هنا ‫لأطلب مساعدتك بالرغم من شعوري بالخزي.
I hope you will understand.
‫آمل أن تتفهم.
I thought you were always sure of yourself even before Lord Sangheon and His Majesty.
‫ظننت أنك لطالما كنت واثقًا من نفسك ‫حتى أمام اللورد "سانغهيون" وجلالته.
But even you, the Minister of Personnel, needs help
‫لكن حتى أنت، ‫وزير شؤون الموظفين، تحتاج إلى مساعدة
when it concerns your child.
‫عندما يتعلق الأمر بابنتك.
Please wait over there. I'll bring out the physician.
‫انتظرا هناك من فضلكما، سأحضر الطبيب.
I apologized to that girl.
‫اعتذرت لتلك الفتاة.
I didn't do it just because you told me to.
‫لم أفعل ذلك لأنك طلبت مني فحسب.
I also know what is right and wrong.
‫أنا أعرف أيضًا ما هو الصواب وما هو الخطأ.
I came by to tell you that.
‫أتيت لأخبرك بذلك.
Are you that surprised to see me here?
‫هل تفاجأت برؤيتي هنا إلى هذه الدرجة؟
Or are you touched that I came to see you?
‫أم هل تأثرت لأنني أتيت لرؤيتك؟
Who are you?
‫من أنت؟
You…
‫أنت…
Where is that physician?
‫أين ذلك الطبيب؟
Gosh. What are you doing here?
‫يا للهول، ماذا تفعل هنا؟
LIST OF COURT MAIDS
‫"قائمة خادمات البلاط"
What is this?
‫ما هذا؟
I might have been a bit harsh the other day.
‫ربما كنت قاسيًا بعض الشيء في ذلك اليوم.
That court maid…
‫خادمة البلاط تلك…
died.
‫ماتت.
It happened not long after leaving the palace
‫حدث الأمر بعد مغادرة القصر بفترة قصيرة
due to an illness.
‫بسبب المرض.
DAM-I
‫"دامي"
LEFT THE PALACE DUE TO ILLNESS
‫"غادرت القصر بسبب المرض"
I see.
‫فهمت.
That explains why you couldn't remember her.
‫هذا يفسر عدم قدرتك على تذكّرها.
That girl…
‫لا بد…
must have been someone quite special to you.
‫أن تلك الفتاة كانت مميزة فعلًا بالنسبة لك.
She was my first love.
‫كانت حبي الأول.
She helped me become a better person.
‫ساعدتني في أن أصبح شخصًا أفضل.
I wanted
‫أردت…
to thank her…
‫أن أشكرها…
if I ever saw her again.
‫لو أنني رأيتها مجددًا.
I guess I won't be able to.
‫أظن أنني لن أستطيع فعل ذلك.
It wasn't my intention to make you concerned, Your Royal Highness.
‫لم أكن أنوي أن أثير قلقك يا صاحب السموّ.
My apologies.
‫أعتذر.
NOKUNGAK
‫"نوكونغاك"
Goodness. What are you doing?
‫يا للهول، ماذا تفعل؟
I'm helping you with the laundry.
‫أساعدك في الغسيل.
Do you know the story behind these deserted quarters?
‫هل تعرف قصة هذا المسكن المهجور؟
What story?
‫أي قصة؟
A long time ago, a court maid loved a man who lived outside the palace.
‫منذ زمن بعيد، ‫أحبّت خادمة بلاط رجلًا يعيش خارج القصر.
And she couldn't overcome the hopelessness of unfulfilled love.
‫ولم تستطع التغلب على اليأس ‫الناجم عن الحب الذي لم يكتمل.
So she hanged herself here.
‫لذا شنقت نفسها هنا.
Afterward, people stopped coming here.
‫بعد ذلك، توقف الناس عن المجيء إلى هنا.
And the deserted quarters became an eyesore.
‫وأصبح المسكن المهجور مزعجًا.
So the Kings tried to tear this place down over many generations.
‫حاول الملوك هدم هذا المكان ‫على مر أجيال عديدة.
But anyone who tried to demolish this place either got sick or died
‫لكن كل من حاول هدم هذا المكان مرض أو مات
as if they'd been cursed. That's what I heard.
‫كما لو أن لعنة أصابته، هذا ما سمعته.
After that, they weren't able to tear this place down.
‫بعد ذلك، لم يتمكنوا من هدم هذا المكان.
So instead, they just closed it.
‫لذا بدلًا من ذلك، أغلقوه فحسب.
What?
‫ماذا؟
Aren't you scared to be alone in a place like this?
‫ألا تخافين البقاء وحيدة في مكان كهذا؟
Why would I be scared?
‫لماذا قد أخاف؟
I like that no one comes here thanks to that story.
‫يعجبني أن أحدًا لا يأتي ‫إلى هنا بفضل تلك القصة.
NOKUNGAK
‫"نوكونغاك"
-A ghost! -You startled me!
‫- شبح! ‫- أفزعتني!
Stop. Wait up!
‫توقفي، انتظري!
Wait until I catch you!
‫انتظري حتى أُمسك بك!
Come on, wait up! I'm scared!
‫كفاك، انتظري، أنا خائف!
I thought you'd be busy with the reception. What brings you here?
‫ظننت أنك ستكون مشغولًا ‫بالاستقبال، ما الذي جاء بك إلى هنا؟
I heard that the Crown Prince ended the lecture early today.
‫سمعت أن وليّ العهد أنهى ‫المحاضرة باكرًا اليوم.
Is there something wrong?
‫هل هناك خطب ما؟
Oh, he went to his spot.
‫قد ذهب إلى مكانه المفضل.
You know, the spot he always goes to when he has a lot on his mind.
‫المكان الذي يذهب ‫إليه دائمًا عندما يكون فكره مشغولًا.
This place is a true gem.
‫هذا المكان رائع حقًا.
You won't find a place breezier than here.
‫لن تجد مكانًا يهبّ فيه النسيم أكثر من هذا.
Hyun.
‫"هيون".
I thought you'd be in Ganghwa for the reception.
‫ظننت أنك ستكون ‫في "غانغهوا" من أجل الاستقبال.
You haven't left yet?
‫ألم تغادر بعد؟
I postponed it to tomorrow.
‫أجّلت ذلك إلى الغد.
I have a more important matter to take care of today.
‫يجب أن أهتم بمسألة أكثر أهمية اليوم.
An important matter? What is it?
‫مسألة مهمة؟ ما الأمر؟
You mentioned you wanted to taste this the other day.
‫ذكرت أنك تريد تذوّق هذا في ذلك اليوم.
I happened to remember what you said.
‫صادف أن تذكرت ما قلته.
I hope
‫آمل…
you didn't delay your trip because of this.
‫أنك لم تؤجل رحلتك بسبب هذا.
Well, let's say it was one of many reasons.
‫حسنًا، لنقل إنه كان واحدًا من أسباب عديدة.
You always told me you wanted to run free.
‫لطالما أخبرتني أنك تريد أن تكون حرًا.
Why do you always stop here?
‫لماذا تتوقف هنا دائمًا؟
Because I have to go back to the palace.
‫لأنه عليّ العودة إلى القصر.
And this is the extent…
‫وهذا هو مدى…
of the path I know.
‫الطريق الذي أعرفه.
You told me
‫قلت لي
that you had traveled someplace far, right?
‫إنك سافرت إلى مكان بعيد، صحيح؟
What did you find far away from here?
‫ماذا وجدت بعيدًا عن هنا؟
If you keep going straight past the gate,
‫إذا استمررت ‫في المشي بشكل مستقيم وتجاوزت البوابة،
is it true
‫هل صحيح
that you'll see the ocean, which has an unknown length and depth?
‫أنك سترى المحيط، ‫والذي له امتداد وعمق غير معروفين؟
Does that really exist?
‫هل هذا موجود حقًا؟
Yes. It does.
‫نعم، موجود.
And there is a ship with a big sail too.
‫وهناك سفينة لها شراع كبير أيضًا.
Once you get on the ship, you can go anywhere.
‫حالما تصعد على متن السفينة، ‫يمكنك الذهاب إلى أي مكان.
Even if it's very far.
‫حتى لو كان بعيدًا جدًا.
If you ask me for directions, I'll give them to you.
‫إن سألتني عن الاتجاهات فسأخبرك بها.
Always.
‫دائمًا.
You only have an hour.
‫لديك ساعة واحدة فقط.
Unfortunately, the sun will set in an hour.
‫للأسف، ستغرب الشمس خلال ساعة.
So enjoy the breeze and the view until then.
‫لذا استمتع بالنسيم والمنظر حتى ذلك الحين.
I have been working hard lately.
‫كنت أعمل بجد مؤخرًا.
So I cannot stop dozing off.
‫لذا لا يمكنني التوقف عن النوم.
Flowers for the Crown Prince's quarters?
‫زهور لجناح وليّ العهد؟
I wasn't informed about this.
‫لم يخبرني أحد بشأن ذلك.
Can you tell me what they are for?
‫هل يمكنك أن تخبرني ما الغرض منها؟
Well…
‫حسنًا…
The thing is…
‫الأمر هو…
If it's too much to ask, can't I just get some flower seeds?
‫إن كان هذا الطلب صعبًا، هل يمكنني ‫أن أحصل على بعض بذور الأزهار فحسب؟
Well, I'm done planting the flowers, and I do have some left.
‫حسنًا، انتهيت ‫من زراعة الأزهار، وما زال لديّ بعضها.
Please give me a few.
‫أعطني القليل منها رجاءً.
Can't you give me some of the flowers?
‫ألا يمكنك أن تعطيني بعضًا من الأزهار؟
Why do you have them?
‫لماذا تحمل هذه معك؟
These? I want to plant some flowers.
‫هذه؟ أريد أن أزرع بعض الأزهار.
I have a place in mind.
‫أفكر في مكان محدد.
I see.
‫فهمت.
Thank you
‫شكرًا لك
for looking into her record.
‫على البحث في سجلّها.
Sure.
‫على الرحب.
I heard that you are attending lectures again.
‫سمعت أنك ستحضر المحاضرات مجددًا.
I know you've been busy lately.
‫أعلم أنك كنت مشغولًا مؤخرًا.
Royal Tutor Jung!
‫أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ"!
What are you doing? You have a big problem!
‫ماذا تفعل؟ أنت تواجه مشكلة كبيرة!
What problem?
‫أي مشكلة؟
Well, the Minister of Personnel
‫في الحقيقة،
lodged an appeal for your resignation.
‫قدّم وزير شؤون الموظفين ‫التماسًا لاستقالتك.
For my resignation?
‫لاستقالتي أنا؟
Royal Tutor Jung Ji-un of the Crown Prince
‫"جي أون جونغ"، المعلّم الملكي لوليّ العهد
is in fact Samgaebang's real physician?
‫هو في الواقع طبيب "سامغايبانغ" الحقيقي؟
Unfortunately, he is, Your Majesty.
‫لسوء الحظ، إنه كذلك جلالتك.
-My goodness. -What? He is?
‫- يا للهول. ‫- ماذا؟ حقًا؟
If what you're telling me is the truth,
‫إن كان ما تقوله هو الحقيقة،
who is the imprisoned physician at Hanseong Magistracy?
‫فمن هو الطبيب المسجون ‫في هيئة القضاء في "هانسيونغ"؟
He used to be a mere assistant at Samgaebang.
‫كان مجرد مساعد في "سامغايبانغ".
Left State Councilor, I need you to explain this.
‫يا مستشار الدولة الأيسر، ‫أريدك أن تشرح لي هذا.
You were the one who recommended Royal Tutor Jung.
‫أنت من أوصيت بالمعلّم الملكي "جونغ".
Everything the Minister of Personnel said is true.
‫كل ما قاله وزير شؤون الموظفين صحيح.
Then are you telling us that you recommended
‫إذًا هل تخبرنا أنك أوصيت
a lowly physician from the street
‫بطبيب وضيع من الشارع
to be the Crown Prince's royal tutor despite knowing his history?
‫ليكون المعلّم الملكي لوليّ العهد ‫بالرغم من معرفتك بتاريخه؟
He may be a lowly physician from the street.
‫قد يكون طبيبًا وضيعًا من الشارع.
But he's a royal tutor if he has wisdom to share.
‫لكنه معلّم ملكي إن كان لديه حكمة يشاركها.
Your Majesty, didn't you compliment his wisdom during the last exam?
‫جلالتك، ألم تثن ‫على حكمته في الاختبار الأخير؟
Jung Ji-un displays great character
‫يُظهر "جي أون جونغ" شخصية رائعة
and an excellent literary talent compared to other royal tutors.
‫وموهبة أدبية ممتازة ‫مقارنة بالمعلّمين الملكيين الآخرين.
This good-natured man ran a pharmacy called Samgaebang to share
‫كان هذا الرجل اللطيف ‫يدير صيدلية تُدعى "سامغايبانغ"
his medical knowledge with the people.
‫ليشارك معرفته الطبية مع الناس.
You cannot possibly hold this act of kindness against him.
‫لا يمكنك لومه على هذا التصرف الكريم.
His history of running a pharmacy isn't the problem.
‫تاريخه في إدارة الصيدلية ليس المشكلة.
Hiding this from His Majesty and the Crown Prince
‫إخفاء هذا عن جلالة الملك ووليّ العهد
is a more serious crime. Don't you agree?
‫جريمة أكثر خطورة، ألا توافقني الرأي؟
On top of that, if the Inspector General
‫علاوة على ذلك، إن كان المفتش العام
ordered to close down Samgaebang for corrupting public morals,
‫قد أمر بإغلاق "سامغايبانغ" ‫بسبب إفساد الأخلاق العامة،
I'm sure there must have been a bigger problem than meets the eye.
‫فأنا واثق أنه كانت هناك مشكلة ‫أكبر مما يبدو عليه الأمر.
I resented the Minister of Personnel for not siding with me before.
‫كرهت وزير شؤون الموظفين ‫لعدم وقوفه إلى جانبي من قبل.
But he definitely tipped the scales in my favor.
‫لكنه قلب الموازين لصالحي بالتأكيد.
He's indeed a difficult man to figure out.
‫إنه رجل يصعب فهمه حقًا.
It's too early to celebrate.
‫من المبكر جدًا أن نحتفل بذلك.
Don't you know Lord Sangheon?
‫ألا تعرفين اللورد "سانغهيون"؟
He'll probably try to make this go away by reprimanding a lecturer.
‫ربما سيحاول أن ينهي الأمر ‫من خلال تأنيب أحد المعلّمين.
That's why we must help him.
‫لهذا السبب يجب أن نساعده.
His Majesty expects many great things from Prince Jehyeon.
‫جلالته ينتظر الكثير ‫من الأمور الرائعة من الأمير "جيهيون".
Don't you think it's time for us to step up
‫ألا تظن أنه حان الوقت كي نتدخل
and weaken the influence of Lord Sangheon and the Crown Prince?
‫ونضعف نفوذ اللورد "سانغهيون" ووليّ العهد؟
Why did you let them live?
‫لماذا تركتهما على قيد الحياة؟
I'll explain everything to the Minister of Personnel in person.
‫سأشرح كل شيء لوزير شؤون الموظفين شخصيًا.
Do you think you can easily hold sway over him?
‫هل تظن أن بإمكانك التأثير عليه بسهولة؟
I practically spoon-fed you, but you couldn't even handle that
‫فعليًا، وجّهتك في كل شيء، ‫لكنك لم تستطع التعامل مع ذلك حتى
and made a mess.
‫وأحدثت فوضى.
I'm sorry, my lord.
‫أنا آسف يا سيدي.
I will do whatever it takes to handle this matter.
‫سأفعل كل ما يتطلبه الأمر ‫للتعامل مع هذا الأمر.
Of course you will
‫بالطبع ستفعل ذلك
because your precious son's life will depend on it.
‫لأن حياة ابنك العزيز ستتوقف على ذلك.
I must talk to the Minister of Personnel.
‫يجب أن أتحدث إلى وزير شؤون الموظفين.
-I only need a moment of his time. -No.
‫- أحتاج إلى لحظة من وقته فحسب. ‫- لا.
He said he wouldn't meet with you until His Majesty approves of it.
‫قال إنه لن يلتقي بك ‫حتى يوافق جلالته على ذلك.
Please leave.
‫غادر من فضلك.
Wait. I only need a moment of his time.
‫مهلًا، أحتاج إلى لحظة من وقته فحسب.
How dare you!
‫كيف تجرؤ!
I want you to release them now.
‫أريدك أن تطلق سراحهما الآن.
I'll take responsibility for everything.
‫سأتحمل مسؤولية كل شيء.
How will you take responsibility?
‫كيف ستتحمل المسؤولية؟
You deceived the royal family, so even your life is in danger.
‫خدعت العائلة المالكة، ‫لذا حتى حياتك في خطر.
How will you take responsibility for it?
‫كيف ستتحمل مسؤولية الأمر؟
You could have punished just me from the beginning.
‫كان يمكنك أن تعاقبني أنا فقط منذ البداية.
Why are you torturing my innocent friends and putting everyone in danger?
‫لماذا تعذب ‫صديقيّ البريئين وتعرّض الجميع للخطر؟
His Majesty will decide
‫سيتخذ جلالته القرار
on your position in three days at the morning assembly.
‫بخصوص منصبك ‫خلال ثلاثة أيام في الاجتماع الصباحي.
Do whatever it takes to secure your position until then.
‫افعل كل ما يلزم لتضمن منصبك حتى ذلك الحين.
If you fail,
‫إن فشلت،
those friends you cherish, the both of us,
‫فإن صديقيك العزيزين ونحن الاثنين
and your dear mother
‫وأمك العزيزة
won't be able to live another day.
‫لن نكون قادرين على العيش ليوم آخر.
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
Tell me. What happened?
‫أخبرني، ماذا حدث؟
It looks like things have gotten pretty serious.
‫يبدو أن الأمور قد ازدادت خطورة.
Not only will His Majesty punish Royal Tutor Jung,
‫لن يعاقب جلالته ‫المعلّم الملكي "جونغ" فحسب،
but he will also punish his father for turning a blind eye on his son.
‫لكنه سيعاقب والده أيضًا ‫لأنه غضّ النظر عن ابنه.
I doubt Inspector Jung Seok-jo was acting alone.
‫أشكّ في أن المفتش "سيوك جو جونغ" ‫كان يتصرف بمفرده.
Everyone must know that he was only doing
‫يجب أن يعرف الجميع أنه لم يكن يفعل
what my maternal grandfather
‫إلا ما أمره به
told him to do.
‫جدّي من جهة أمي.
Anyway, I say it all worked out.
‫على أي حال، أرى أن الأمر نجح.
You weren't exactly keen on them.
‫لم تكن مقتنعًا بهما.
So driving them out of the palace--
‫لذا فإن طردهما من القصر…
It's getting late. You can go now.
‫تأخر الوقت، يمكنك الذهاب الآن.
Pardon?
‫عفوًا؟
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‫حسنًا يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
Are you bothered by the scandal regarding Royal Tutor Jung?
‫هل أنت منزعجة من الفضيحة المتعلقة ‫بالمعلّم الملكي "جونغ"؟
He's Jung Seok-jo's son.
‫إنه ابن "سيوك جو جونغ".
His father was responsible for murdering the Prince.
‫والده كان مسؤولًا عن قتل الأمير.
No. His father tried to kill you, Your Royal Highness.
‫لا، حاول والده ‫أن يقتلك يا صاحبة السموّ الملكي.
I know.
‫أعرف.
I do.
‫أعرف هذا بالتأكيد.
You must not forget that.
‫عليك ألّا تنسي ذلك.
Never.
‫أبدًا.
Please do not forget that.
‫أرجو ألّا تنسي ذلك.
It's all my fault that he's in trouble.
‫إنه واقع في مشكلة بسببي.
The Minister of Personnel scared me out of my wits.
‫أخافني وزير شؤون الموظفين كثيرًا.
Do you really think it's not too late?
‫هل تظن حقًا أن الأوان لم يفت؟
If I tell them that I'm the real physician at Samgaebang,
‫إذا أخبرتهم ‫أنني الطبيب الحقيقي في "سامغايبانغ"،
Yeong-ji and Ji-un will be able to live, right?
‫فإن "يونغ جي" و"جي أون" ‫سيتمكنان من العيش، صحيح؟
What nonsense is that?
‫ما هذا الهراء؟
The Inspector… No. Ji-un's father told me
‫المفتش…لا، والد "جي أون" أخبرني
that if I recant my statement, everyone will be okay.
‫أنني إذا تراجعت ‫عن أقوالي، سيكون الجميع بخير.
You idiot. Do you really buy that?
‫أيها الأحمق، هل تصدق هذا حقًا؟
Hearing that he might find a nice spot to bury you is more plausible. You dimwit.
‫لو قلت إنه يبحث عن مكان جميل ليدفنك فيه ‫لكان كلامك منطقيًا أكثر أيها الغبي.
What am I supposed to do?
‫ماذا يُفترض بي أن أفعل؟
Ji-un is about to die because of me.
‫سيموت "جي أون" بسببي.
Chief Gu. You have to get out of here now.
‫أيها القائد "غو"، يجب أن تخرج من هنا الآن.
I'll tell Royal Tutor Jung everything.
‫سأخبر المعلّم الملكي "جونغ" بكل شيء.
So don't do anything stupid. And say you don't know anything.
‫لذا لا ترتكب أي حماقة، ‫وقُل إنك لا تعرف شيئًا.
Stick to that. Got it?
‫التزم بذلك، هل فهمت؟
Come on, hurry up!
‫هيا، أسرع!
You don't know anything.
‫أنت لا تعرف شيئًا.
My lady!
‫سيدتي!
-My lady. -Father.
‫- سيدتي. ‫- أبي.
What are you doing?
‫ماذا تفعلين؟
They are about to get hurt because of me.
‫إنهم على وشك أن يتأذّوا بسببي.
Father. Please let it slide just this once.
‫أبي، أرجوك أن تتغاضى ‫عن الأمر هذه المرة فقط.
They aren't bad people.
‫ليسوا أشرارًا.
I'm sure it wasn't their intention.
‫أنا واثقة أنها لم تكن نيتهم.
How can we be certain that they aren't bad people?
‫كيف يمكننا التأكد من أنهم ليسوا أشرارًا؟
I will only see them as either innocent or guilty.
‫لن أنظر إليهم ‫إلا على أنهم أبرياء أو مذنبون.
Father. Please.
‫أبي، أرجوك.
That's enough. I already reported it to His Majesty.
‫هذا يكفي، سبق وأبلغت جلالته بالأمر.
The decision is up to His Majesty.
‫إن القرار في يد صاحب الجلالة.
Father!
‫أبي!
His Majesty will issue a royal order at tomorrow's morning assembly.
‫سيُصدر جلالته أمرًا ملكيًا ‫في الاجتماع الصباحي غدًا.
It's unfortunate, but I believe today
‫هذا مؤسف، لكن أظن أن اليوم
will be the last time I see you.
‫ستكون آخر مرة أراك فيها.
You haven't been here long,
‫لم تبق هنا لفترة طويلة،
but I will remember your lectures as somewhat useful.
‫لكنني سأتذكر أن محاضراتك مفيدة إلى حد ما.
I cannot leave the palace yet.
‫لا يمكنني مغادرة القصر الآن.
I'm in need of your help.
‫أحتاج إلى مساعدتك.
You are the only person who can help me now.
‫أنت الشخص الوحيد الذي يمكنه مساعدتي الآن.
Why would I help you?
‫لماذا قد أساعدك؟
Did you forget that I, of all people, wanted you gone
‫هل نسيت أنني أنا بالذات أردتك أن ترحل
when you first came to the palace?
‫عندما أتيت إلى القصر لأول مرة؟
I know that. That's why I'm asking you for your help.
‫أعرف ذلك، لهذا السبب أطلب مساعدتك.
You knew from the beginning that I was a physician at Samgaebang.
‫كنت تعرف منذ البداية ‫أنني طبيب في "سامغايبانغ".
But you accepted me as your lecturer.
‫لكنك قبلت بي كمعلّم لك.
It was because I lost the bet. I did make a promise after all.
‫كان هذا لأنني خسرت الرهان، ‫فقد قطعت وعدًا في النهاية.
Could you
‫هل يمكنك
keep your promise one more time?
‫الوفاء بوعدك مرة أخرى؟
Gosh.
‫يا للهول.
Unfortunately, there is nothing I can do for you.
‫لسوء الحظ، ‫لا يمكنني أن أفعل شيئًا من أجلك.
So I advise you to stop asking.
‫لذا أنصحك أن تتوقف عن طرح الأسئلة.
Royal Tutor Jung…
‫أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ"…
There you are.
‫ها أنت ذا.
Where have you been? I looked everywhere for you.
‫أين كنت؟ بحثت عنك في كل مكان.
What about Jil-geum? He's okay, right?
‫ماذا عن "جيل غيوم"؟ إنه بخير، صحيح؟
It's about your father.
‫الأمر يتعلق بوالدك.
I think he's going to pin everything on him. What should we do?
‫أظن أنه سيحمّله ‫مسؤولية كل شيء، ماذا يجب أن نفعل؟
I don't know what to do. I can neither stop him nor support him.
‫لا أعرف ماذا أفعل، ‫لا يمكنني أن أوقفه ولا أن أدعمه.
Chief Gu!
‫أيها القائد "غو"!
What are you talking about?
‫ما الذي تتحدث عنه؟
That fool wants to save you and Yeong-ji.
‫ذلك الأحمق يريد إنقاذك أنت و"يونغ جي".
You don't think he'll kill them, right?
‫أنت لا تظن أنه سيقتلهما، صحيح؟
After all, you cherish them like your family. Right?
‫في النهاية، أنت تهتم لأمرهما ‫وكأنهما فردان من عائلتك، صحيح؟
No… Jil-geum. No.
‫لا…"جيل غيوم"، لا.
Hey, wait. Royal Tutor Jung!
‫مهلًا، أيها المعلّم الملكي "جونغ"!
Your Royal Highness, Prince Jaeun is here to see you.
‫يا صاحب السموّ، حضر الأمير "جايون" لرؤيتك.
Hyun.
‫"هيون".
Was your trip to Ganghwa pleasant?
‫هل كانت رحلتك إلى "غانغهوا" ممتعة؟
Yes.
‫نعم.
I have something to tell you.
‫لديّ ما أخبرك به.
What is it?
‫ما الأمر؟
Royal Tutor Jung ran Samgaebang
‫المعلّم الملكي كان يدير "سامغايبانغ"
with the sole purpose of helping poor kids from the slums.
‫بهدف وحيد وهو مساعدة الأطفال الفقراء ‫الذين يعيشون في الأحياء الفقيرة.
Is that it?
‫هل هذا كل ما في الأمر؟
Yes, Your Royal Highness.
‫نعم يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
He only accepted the position at the palace
‫لم يقبل بالمنصب في القصر
to save his friends from Samgaebang.
‫إلا لينقذ صديقيه العاملين في "سامغايبانغ".
He never wanted the title.
‫لم يرغب في المنصب قط.
-Why are you telling me this? -Because--
‫- لماذا تخبرني بهذا؟ ‫- لأن…
I know that Jung Ji-un is an old friend of yours.
‫أعرف أن "جي أون جونغ" صديق قديم لك.
I understand that you want to help him.
‫أفهم أنك تريد مساعدته.
But this is pointless.
‫لكن لا جدوى من هذا.
Whatever the reason is,
‫مهما كان السبب،
he still broke the code of morals and deceived our family.
‫فقد خرق القانون الأخلاقي وخدع عائلتنا.
His actions will not be forgiven.
‫لن يُسامح على أفعاله.
He may be my friend, but he's also your royal tutor.
‫قد يكون صديقي، لكنه معلّمك الملكي أيضًا.
I'm tired.
‫أنا مُتعب.
I'm sure you are exhausted from the trip.
‫أنا متأكد أنك مُرهق من الرحلة.
We should talk some other time.
‫يجب أن نتحدث في وقت لاحق.
I cannot leave the palace yet.
‫لا يمكنني مغادرة القصر الآن.
I'm in need of your help.
‫أحتاج إلى مساعدتك.
You're the only person who can help me now.
‫أنت الشخص الوحيد الذي يمكنه مساعدتي الآن.
What did you wish for?
‫ماذا تمنيت؟
Do you remember the slum we passed by earlier on our way here?
‫هل تتذكر الحي الفقير ‫الذي مررنا به سابقًا في طريقنا إلى هنا؟
What?
‫ماذا؟
I wished that
‫قد تمنيت
the kids in the slum would be well fed and grow up in good health.
‫أن يحصل أطفال الأحياء الفقيرة ‫على طعام جيد ليكبروا ويعيشوا بصحة جيدة.
That's what I wrote down.
‫هذا ما كتبته.
What?
‫ماذا؟
It's their parents' job to take care of them.
‫من واجب أهلهم أن يعتنوا بهم.
Why…
‫لماذا…
Most of them are orphans.
‫معظمهم أيتام.
I grew up there as an orphan too.
‫ترعرعت هناك كيتيمة أيضًا.
My heart breaks for them,
‫أشعر بالأسى عليهم،
but I don't have the means to help them.
‫لكنني لا أملك الوسائل لمساعدتهم.
So if I make a wish for them,
‫لذا إن تمنيت لهم أمنية،
perhaps, someone might help them one day.
‫فربما يساعدهم أحد ما في يوم من الأيام.
Right. What did you wish for?
‫صحيح، ماذا تمنيت؟
Me?
‫أنا؟
Well, I…
‫حسنًا، أنا…
Hold on, Dam-i.
‫مهلًا يا "دامي".
Young Master.
‫أيها السيد الشاب.
Why did you do that?
‫لماذا فعلت ذلك؟
Well, after hearing your wish,
‫في الواقع، بعد أن سمعت أمنيتك،
my wish sounded petty and selfish.
‫بدت أمنيتي تافهة وأنانية.
-Pardon? -So I changed mine.
‫- عفوًا؟ ‫- لذا غيّرت أمنيتي.
My wish is to become that someone who can help those kids.
‫أمنيتي هي أن أصبح ذلك الشخص ‫الذي يمكنه مساعدة أولئك الأطفال.
Should I not have mentioned it to him?
‫هل كان عليّ ألّا أخبره بذلك؟
No.
‫لا.
If I did, Jil-geum would be framed for everything and end up dead.
‫لو لم أخبره، كانت ستُلفّق التهمة ‫لـ"جيل غيوم" في كل شيء وسيموت في النهاية.
I couldn't let that happen to him. Of course, not.
‫لا يمكنني السماح بحدوث ذلك له، بالطبع لا.
Right!
‫صحيح!
Royal Tutor Jung is on it now. I'm sure he has come up with a plan.
‫يعمل المعلّم الملكي "جونغ" ‫على ذلك الآن، أنا واثق أن لديه خطة ما.
I doubt that he's going to kill his own son. Right.
‫أشكّ في أنه سيقتل ابنه، صحيح.
No. No way.
‫لا، مستحيل.
What if Royal Tutor Jung gets killed too?
‫ماذا لو قُتل المعلّم الملكي "جونغ" أيضًا؟
The Inspector is capable of doing so.
‫المفتش قادر على فعل ذلك.
Gosh. This is driving me crazy!
‫يا للهول، هذا يقودني إلى الجنون!
Goodness! What do I do now?
‫يا للهول! ماذا يجب أن أفعل الآن؟
Who is going to get killed?
‫من الذي سيُقتل؟
Who are you?
‫من أنتم؟
Wait. Where are we going?
‫مهلًا، إلى أين سنذهب؟
Where are you taking me?
‫إلى أين تأخذانني؟
Sir.
‫سيدي.
-Yeong-ji! -Jil-geum!
‫- "يونغ جي"! ‫- "جيل غيوم"!
Stop!
‫توقفوا!
-Ji-un!
‫- "جي أون"!
Are you…
‫هل…
-really going to kill them too? -Step aside.
‫- ستقتلهما أيضًا حقًا؟ ‫- تنحّ جانبًا.
How much more can you possibly disappoint me?
‫إلى متى يمكنك أن تستمر في تخييب أملي؟
I told you to step aside.
‫طلبت منك أن تتنحى جانبًا.
Are you really going to kill me?
‫هل ستقتلني حقًا؟
Let them go.
‫أطلق سراحهما.
Please.
‫أرجوك.
They will live someplace else.
‫سيعيشان في مكان آخر.
Just tell yourself that.
‫أقنع نفسك بذلك وحسب.
That is the only thing you can do.
‫هذا كل ما يمكنك فعله.
-Ji-un!
‫- "جي أون"!
No!
‫لا!
-What are you doing? -If I do this…
‫- ماذا تفعل؟ ‫- إن فعلت هذا…
you have no reason to kill them.
‫لن يكون لديك سبب لقتلهما.
If you lay a finger on them,
‫إذا ألحقت بهما أي أذى،
I will not forgive you
‫فلن أسامحك
even if you are my father!
‫حتى لو كنت والدي!
-Ji-un!
‫- "جي أون"!
Lock him up until I return.
‫احبساه حتى أعود.
Take the girl away from here for now.
‫خُذ الفتاة بعيدًا من هنا الآن.
Jil-geum!
‫"جيل غيوم"!
-Jil-geum! -Yeong-ji!
‫- "جيل غيوم"! ‫- "يونغ جي"!
Write down what I say.
‫اكتب ما أقوله.
You were scared, so you lied.
‫كنت خائفًا، لذلك كذبت.
And you are the physician at Samgaebang.
‫وأنت الطبيب في "سامغايبانغ".
You were scared of your punishment,
‫كنت خائفًا من عقابك،
so you bought off guards and escaped. Got it?
‫لذا قمت برشوة الحراس وهربت، هل فهمت؟
No…
‫لا…
Please spare me.
‫أرجوك اصفح عني.
Please let me live!
‫أرجوك دعني أعيش!
It's my fault. Please don't kill me.
‫إنه خطئي، أرجوك لا تقتلني.
I heard that Ji-un saved you and that girl
‫سمعت أن "جي أون" أنقذك أنت وتلك الفتاة
when your lives were in danger.
‫حين كانت حياتكما في خطر.
You can pay him back
‫يمكنك سداد الدين
right now.
‫الآن.
Yeong-ji.
‫"يونغ جي".
Please spare me…
‫أرجوك اصفح عني…
Please spare me.
‫أرجوك اصفح عني.
I AM THE PHYSICIAN OF SAMGAEBANG
‫"أنا طبيب (سامغايبانغ)"
I ESCAPED
‫"هربت"
BANG JIL-GEUM
‫"جيل غيوم بانغ"
Wait. As you promised,
‫مهلًا، كما وعدت،
please spare Ji-un and Yeong-ji.
‫أرجوك أن تعفو عن "جي أون" و"يونغ جي".
Please don't kill them.
‫أرجوك لا تقتلهما.
Please…
‫أرجوك…
Please let them live.
‫أرجوك أن تدعهما يعيشان.
I noticed that some crooks secretly took the prisoners
‫لاحظت أن بعض المحتالين أخرجوا ‫السجينين سرًا
from Hanseong Magistracy.
‫من هيئة القضاء في "هانسيونغ".
I order you as the Crown Prince.
‫آمرك بصفتي وليّ العهد.
Hand over the prisoners.
‫سلّم السجناء.
If you do,
‫إن فعلت ذلك
no one will shed a drop of blood here tonight.
‫فلن يُريق أحد قطرة دم واحدة هنا الليلة.
Did Lord Sangheon approve of this?
‫هل وافق اللورد "سانغهيون" على هذا؟
Did you not hear me?
‫ألم تسمعني؟
I ordered you as the Crown Prince of Joseon.
‫أمرتك بذلك بصفتي وليّ عهد "جوسون".
Unless there is a royal command,
‫ما لم يصدر أمر ملكيّ،
no one can dare to disapprove of my order.
‫لا يمكن لأحد أن يجرؤ على رفض أمري.
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
Is that what you truly believe?
‫هل هذا ما تظنه حقًا؟
You must not agree with me
‫لا بد أنك لا توافقني الرأي
seeing how
‫على اعتبار
you won't lower your sword.
‫أنك لم تخفض سيفك.
If he so much as moves his hand,
‫إن قام بتحريك يده حتى
bring me
‫فأحضر لي
his head in an instant.
‫رأسه بلمح البصر.
What? You don't think I can go through with this?
‫ماذا؟ ألا تظن أن بإمكاني فعل هذا؟
I doubt that my grandfather
‫أشكّ في أن جدّي
will punish his dear grandson for killing his dog.
‫سيعاقب حفيده العزيز لأنه قتل كلبه.
What is going on? Tell me what happened.
‫ماذا يجري؟ أخبرني بما حدث.
Your Royal Highness. You even took the royal guards with you.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي، ‫حتى إنك أخذت الحرس الملكي معك.
What did you do?
‫ماذا فعلت؟
If Lord Sangheon finds out…
‫إذا اكتشف اللورد "سانغهيون" ذلك…
Goodness.
‫بئسًا.
Why did you do that?
‫لماذا فعلت ذلك؟
Why…
‫لماذا…
were you so arrogant, Your Royal Highness?
‫كنت متعجرفًا جدًا يا صاحب السموّ الملكي؟
They took the prisoners.
‫أخرجوا السجينين.
I understand that you ordered them to do so,
‫أفهم أنك أمرتهم بذلك،
but it was wrong.
‫لكن كان ذلك خاطئًا.
So I only did what I was supposed to do.
‫لذلك فعلت ما كان يُفترض بي فعله فحسب.
You're wrong, Your Royal Highness.
‫أنت مخطئ يا صاحب السموّ.
Your moral standards
‫معاييرك الأخلاقية
will not influence your actions.
‫لن تؤثر على أفعالك.
The only thing you must do
‫الشيء الوحيد الذي عليك فعله
is listen to me, your grandfather,
‫هو أن تصغي إليّ، أنا جدك،
and not challenge me.
‫وألّا تتحداني.
That is all.
‫هذا كل شيء.
Do you understand?
‫هل تفهم؟
Do not forget.
‫لا تنس.
The path I choose
‫الطريق الذي أختاره
will be your path.
‫سيكون طريقك.
And if you deviate from that path,
‫وإن انحرفت عن ذلك الطريق،
I will not forgive you,
‫فلن أسامحك،
no matter how much I adore you.
‫مهما بلغ حبي لك.
Get ready.
‫استعد.
It's time for the assembly.
‫حان وقت الاجتماع.
What about my friends? Where are they?
‫ماذا عن صديقيّ؟ أين هما؟
I need to know if they are safe first.
‫أريد أن أعرف إن كانا بأمان أولًا.
You can find out for yourself after the morning assembly.
‫يمكنك أن تكتشف بنفسك بعد الاجتماع الصباحي.
Are they alive?
‫هل هما على قيد الحياة؟
You didn't…
‫أنت…
kill them, right?
‫لم تقتلهما، صحيح؟
Let me sum it up. This man here, Jung Ji-un,
‫دعوني ألخّص الأمر، ‫هذا الرجل هنا، "جي أون جونغ"،
recommended and prescribed
‫كان ينصح ويصف
only expensive and rare medicinal herbs
‫الأعشاب الطبية باهظة الثمن والنادرة فقط
under the pretense of treatments. Is that true?
‫تحت ذريعة العلاج، هل هذا صحيح؟
Yes, that's true.
‫نعم، هذا صحيح.
There is more.
‫هناك المزيد.
When I visited Samgaebang,
‫عندما زرت "سامغايبانغ"،
not only did he make me wait with the people of low birth,
‫لم يجعلني أنتظر ‫مع أبناء الطبقة الدنيا فقط،
but he also humiliated me
‫لكنه أهانني أيضًا
by turning me away at the gate in front of them.
‫بإبعادي عند البوابة أمامهم.
Jung Ji-un neglected the custom of our class system
‫أهمل "جي أون جونغ" ‫العرف الخاص بنظامنا الطبقي
and tarnished the authority of the nobility.
‫ودنّس سلطة النبلاء.
And Inspector Jung Seok-jo protected his son.
‫والمفتش "سيوك جو جونغ" حمى ابنه.
I ask you to punish them, Your Majesty.
‫أطلب منك معاقبتهم يا جلالة الملك.
-Please punish them, Your Majesty.
‫- عاقبهم يا صاحب الجلالة.
Is everything they said true?
‫هل كل ما قالوه صحيح؟
Yes.
‫نعم.
It's true.
‫هذا صحيح.
I will announce the punishment
‫سأعلن عن العقوبة
for Royal Tutor Jung and the prisoners from Samgaebang.
‫التي ستُتخذ بحق المعلّم الملكي "جونغ" ‫والسجينين العاملين في "سامغايبانغ".
Royal Tutor Jung Ji-un
‫المعلّم الملكي "جي أون جونغ"
of the Royal Institute
‫من المعهد الملكي
ran a clinic called Samgaebang as a nobleman and exploited people
‫كان يدير عيادة تُدعى "سامغايبانغ" ‫بصفته رجلًا نبيلًا واستغل الناس،
which resulted in tarnishing the prestige of nobility.
‫الأمر الذي نتج عنه تدنيس هيبة النبلاء.
Moreover, he deceived me and the Crown Prince
‫بالإضافة إلى أنه خدعني أنا ووليّ العهد
and disgraced the royal family.
‫وأهان العائلة الملكية.
The degree of his crime is quite severe.
‫حجم جريمته خطير جدًا.
Therefore,
‫لذلك،
he is no longer a lecturer for the Crown Prince
‫لم يعد معلّمًا لوليّ العهد
and will be banished after facing 50 whips.
‫وسيُنفى بعد أن يُجلد 50 جلدة.
And those who helped him
‫واللذان ساعداه
to run Samgaebang will be forced to do manual labor.
‫في إدارة "سامغايبانغ" ‫سيُجبران على القيام بالأعمال اليدوية.
If that is the punishment I deserve, I will accept it.
‫إن كانت هذه هي العقوبة ‫التي أستحقها فسأقبلها.
But without the prisoners, the punishment can't be executed.
‫لكن من دون السجينين، ‫لا يمكن تنفيذ العقوبة.
My assistants from Samgaebang are missing.
‫مساعداي في "سامغايبانغ" مفقودان.
Please tell me where they are.
‫أخبرني أين هما رجاءً.
What are you talking about?
‫ما الذي تتحدث عنه؟
I thought they were imprisoned at Hanseong Magistracy.
‫ظننت أنهما سُجنا ‫في هيئة القضاء في "هانسيونغ".
Someone took them.
‫شخص ما أخذهما.
Allow me…
‫اسمح لي…
to answer that question.
‫بالإجابة على ذلك السؤال.
-Your Royal Highness. -Your generosity
‫- يا صاحب السموّ الملكي. ‫- إن كرمك
knows no limit, Your Royal Highness.
‫لا يعرف حدودًا يا صاحب السموّ.
Please let me be in charge of receiving the envoys.
‫أرجوك دعني أكون مسؤولًا ‫عن استقبال المبعوثين.
I ask you to put your faith in me this time.
‫أطلب منك أن تثق بي هذه المرة.
Thank you for the warm welcome.
‫شكرًا لكم على هذا الترحيب الحار.
That's enough. You are in the palace of Joseon.
‫هذا يكفي، أنت في قصر "جوسون".
I brought you here to show you something fun, Your Royal Highness.
‫أحضرتك إلى هنا ‫لأريك شيئًا مسليًا يا صاحب السموّ.
What are you doing?
‫ماذا تفعل؟
Your Royal Highness.
‫يا صاحب السموّ الملكي.
I put my faith in you. Yet, you disappointed me.
‫وضعت ثقتي بك، ومع ذلك، خيّبت أملي.
Subtitle translation by: Won-hyang Son
‫ترجمة "مي جمال"